Guide to the Daniel Bell Research Files on U.S. Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement TAM.080
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Daniel Bell Research Files on U.S. Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement
1886-1980
1920-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011
TAM.080
27.75 Linear Feet in 55 manuscript boxes and 1 shared box.
Sociologist Daniel Bell (1919-2011) was a writer and teacher of the history of the American left and of American Labor. He was managing editor of the New Leader in the 1940s, labor editor of Fortune from 1948 to 1958 and is the author of several books and monographs. The papers represent materials gathered by Bell for his writing and research. They include correspondence, clippings, minutes, pamphlets, research notes, articles, reports, congressional testimony and interviews.
Box 1-55
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Daniel Bell in 1969 and 1982. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1969.001 and 1969.003.
Related Archival Materials
American Committee for Cultural Freedom Records (TAM 023)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sociologist Daniel Bell (1919-2011) was a writer and teacher of the history of the American left and of American Labor. A 1939 graduate of City College (CUNY), where he was a member of the Young Peoples Socialist League, Bell was managing editor of the New Leader (a social democratic journal of opinion) in the 1940s, labor editor of Fortune magazine from 1948 to 1958 and author of several books and monographs, including The End of Ideology (1962), The Birth of Post-Industrial Society (1974), and The Cultural Contradictions of Capitalism (1976). Daniel Bell's life and ideas are described in Arguing the World (1997) a documentary film about three notable City College graduates: Bell, Irving Howe, and Nathan Glazer.
Scope and Content Note
The Daniel Bell Research Files on U.S. Communism, Socialism, and the Labor Movement represent materials gathered by Bell for his writing and research. It includes clippings, correspondence, minutes, proceedings, reports, resolutions, circulars and other internal documents; articles, research notes, pamphlets, congressional testimony and interviews. Notable individuals represented herein, sometimes by biographical studies, correspondence, manuscripts, and oral history interview notes include: John Brophy, Earl Browder, Sam Darcy, James Carey, Sidney Hillman, George Meany, H.L. Mitchell, Philip Murray, Norman Thomas, and fellow researcher William Goldsmith.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each box or subseries.
The files are grouped into seven series:
Series I. The Communist Party, U.S.A.: Organization and Policy Development
Subseries I:A: Organization, Policy Development, Political Activities
Subseries I:B: Earl Browder Materials
Subseries I:C: Communist Party Influence in the CIO and in Government re Labor
Subseries I:D: Government and Industry's anti Communist campaign
Series II. The Communist Party, U.S.A. and the American Labor Movement.
Subseries II:A: Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union
Subseries II:B: International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers.
Subseries II:C: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (U.E.)
Subseries II:D: Cloth, Hat, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
Subseries II:E: Joint Board of Cloak, Skirt, Dress and Reefer Makers Unions of N.Y. (ILGWU) & Needle Trades Workers Industrial Union
Subseries II:F: Miscellaneous Unions
Series III. American Labor Unions and Industrial Relations.
Subseries III:A: General studies of the labor movement
Subseries III:B: Labor and Government (articles, news reports, pamphlets, etc.)
Subseries III:C: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen
Subseries III:D: United Auto Workers
Subseries III:E: International Ladies Garment Workers Union (articles & news reports)
Subseries III:F: United Mineworkers of America (articles & news reports)
Subseries III:G: Miscellaneous Articles and News Clippings on Other Unions Subseries III:H: A.F.L. C.I.O. (articles, clippings, notes)
Series IV. The American Socialist Party.
Subseries IV:A: The Socialist Party before World War I
Subseries IV:B: The Socialist Party: 1920s
Subseries IV:C: The Socialist Party: 1930-1933
Subseries IV:D: Young People's Socialist League: 1930-1940
Subseries IV:E: The Socialist Party: 1934-1935 ("Old Guard" - "Militant" split)
Subseries IV:F: The Socialist Party: 1936 ("Old Guard" - "Militant" split)
Subseries IV:G: The Socialist Party: 1937
Subseries IV:H: The Socialist Party: 1938-1939
Subseries IV:I: The Socialist Party and the United Auto Workers, 1937-1941
Subseries IV:J: The Socialist Party: 1940-1941
Subseries IV:K: The Socialist Party: 1942 present
Subseries IV:L: International Socialism
Series V. Princeton Conference on Socialism and American Life.
Series VI. The Communist Party and Its Relations with the American Labor Movement.
Series VII. Addendum: Miscellaneous Writings and Research Materials.
Subseries VII:A: Writings; Research Correspondence & Materials.
Subseries VII:B: Writings; Research Correspondence & Materials.
Pamphlets.; Reports.; Manuscripts for publication.; Testimonies.; Interviews.; Minutes (administrative records); Notes.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Industrial relations |z United States.; Clippings (information artifacts); Socialism -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Cloth Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers' International Union; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946.; Darcy, Samuel, 1905-; Mitchell, H. L. (Harry Leland), 1906-1989; Meany, George, 1894-1980.; Brophy, John, 1883-1963. -- |v Portraits; Bell, Daniel. Marxian socialism in the United States (typescript).; Carey, James B. -- |v Portraits; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the United States and Canada; Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America; Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011; Denitch, Faith. Food Workers Industrial Union (typescript).; Dodd, Bella Visono, 1904-. School of Darkness (typescript).; Goldsmith, William; United Mine Workers of America; United Packinghouse Workers of America; United Public Workers of America; Young People's Socialist League; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Trade Union Educational League (U.S.); Socialist Party (U.S.); Transport Workers Union of America; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Trade Union Unity League (U.S.); United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America; Princeton Conference on Socialism and American Life (1946-1947)
- Series I: The Communist Party U.S.A.
  - Subseries I:A: Organization, Policy Development, Political Activities
    Scope and Content Note
    The news clippings, correspondence, and reading notes assembled here outline the internal development of the CPUSA and are particularly useful for the period 1919-1929. Party minutes, letters, and reports of 1928 and 1929 provide additional information on the labor situation in the needle trades and in mining and on intra Party affairs, in particular on the expulsion of the Lovestoneites in 1929. For the period after 1929 there are articles, newsclippings, and pamphlets illustrating the CPUSA's economic and political orientation. Some of the political activities of the CPUSA are suggested in these reading notes, articles, and news reports concerning the "united fronts" of the 1920s, the Farmer Labor movements of 1922-1925, Henry Wallace, and Vito Marcantonio.
    - Bolshevization, 1925-1929: Notes, Typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Browderism: Theory, Expulsion: Clippings, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CPUSA Internal Documents, 1920s (Factionalism, etc.), undated, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Duclos, Jacques. Notes on the Dissolution of the American Communist Party (ts, 13 p), Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clippings & Ephemera, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Expulsion of Lovestoneites: Copes of Letters & Statements, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Farmer-Labor Maneuvers, 1922-1925: Bell Notes & CP Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Foster, William Z.: Bibliography, Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Foster, William Z.: Monthly Industrial Report of Dist. #3 (Oct. 1924), Nov 1, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 8A)
    - Fronts, 1920s: Notes & Typescripts (Includes: "The United Front: a History/Draper," 7 p), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hall, Gus: Speech at Madison Square Garden, New York, Sep 19, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hungary: Reaction by Intellectuals: Clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter to the ECCI: the Need for Communist Unity (Lovestone, et al), Nov 9, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Materials Owned by the Communism Study of the Fund for the Republic (27 p), Apr 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - National Unemployment Council: Unititled ts on the Unification of All Unemployed Organizations, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1935: (re AFL Convention): Typescript, Reading Notes, Articles & Clippings from the CP Press, undated, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Peter V. Cacchione, Vito Marcantonio: Ephemera re Campaign Tactics, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Political Committee Minutes, Jan 1928-Mar 1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Political Committee Minutes, Apr 1928-Jun 1928 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Progressive Party: News Reports, 1948-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Split in the American CP Articles, Clippings, News Reports, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Wallace, Henry: Clippings & Ephemera; Bell Notes, undated, 1941-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subseries I:B: Earl Browder Materials
    Most of these files contain reports of interest to the CPUSA during World War II. There are, in addition, a report by Earl Browder to the CPUSA National Committee, 1939; a financial report of the Communist Political Association for 1944; and a statement concerning political tactics, 1946.
    - Bittelman, Alex [?]: Important elements for winning the war are…" (ts, 5p.), Jun 3, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Browder, Earl: Plenum Report, Untitled (on intensifying war production), 80 pp., Nov 29, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Browder, Earl: Report to the National Committee, CPUSA Meeting on the 20th Anniversary of the Founding of the Party. Chicago (47 pp), Sep 1, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Communist Political Association: Monthly Financial Rept, Sep 30, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - CPUSA Intensive Pro-War Efforts, General (Includes memos from Roy Hudson, others), 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Early American Writings on (U.S.) Constitution, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Maritime: Special Report (pp. 551-554/5). Covers CPUSA role in the National Maritime Union (by an anti-communist leftist, apparently based on internal sources), Sep 1, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - National Groups as a Problem in Trade Union Work. (Typescript, 12 pp., of a CPUSA meeting, with remarks by Roy Hudson, et al), ca.1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Republican Party: Suggested Workplan for Subcommittees on Labor (confidential to program committee), Nov 19, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Trotskyites, Lovestoneites: Internal Documents (ALP, ILLA - Trotsky, attack on), May 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - United Automobile Workers of America: Factional Conflict. Contents include (principally pertaining to the Aug 1938 trial of Frankensteen, Mortimer, et al.): letters from Homer Martin to Jay Lovestone; a report by Bill (Foster?); transcripts of Jay Lovestone's and Lovestoneite's telephone conversations; statements by Mortimer, et al, 1936, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - United Automobile Workers of America: Intensive War Work, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - United Electrical Workers: Pro-War Efforts (includes Browder correspondence with UE officials, Browder speeches to UE), 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - United Office & Professional Workers of America - War Policy, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries I:C: Communist Party Influence in the CIO and in Government re Labor
    Material on the role of the Party in the labor movement in general is included in this section of the collection. Much of it is congressional testimony concerning communist influence in the Congress of Industrial Organizations and the National Labor Relations Board. The testimony is supplemented by interviews with CIO officials and articles by prominent communists outlining CPUSA labor policy. There are also articles, news reports, and CIO committee reports concerning the CIO's purge of communists in the years 1948-1950. Communist activity in specific unions is dealt with in Series II.
    - Communism, CIO, Anti-War AgitationContents: Contains reports, possibly by Victor Riesel, about strength of Communists and their efforts to keep the U.S. out of WWII, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 14A)
    - Approaching the Drive(ts, 55 leaves); The Drive Begins(ts, 7 leaves)Contents: Two anonymous reports (by Daniel Bell?) discussing the formation and early work of the Steel Workers Organizing Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Carey, James B.: World Federation of Trade Unions - MeetingsContains: Report of CIO Secretary-Treasurer James B. Carey covering meetings of the WFTU Executive Bureau and Executive Committee, April 30 to May 10, 1948 (ts, 17 l.)Contains: Text of conversations between James B. Carey…and Giuseppe Di Vittorio, Secretary General, Italian Confederation of Labor and Fernando Santi, also of DGIL, on March 12, 1948, London (ts, 10 l.)Contents: Report on CIO Representative's Trip to Europe: for immediate release, March 22, 1948 (ts, with appendices, 9 l.), Mar 1948-May 1948 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Catholics (clippings, reports, telegrams), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Centralized Direction of Labor Policy in the United States Steel Corporation / National Labor Relations Board Memorandum from Jacob Karro to David J. Saposs (37 leaves), Feb 2, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - CIO Charges Against Communist UnionsContents: Report of the Committees to Investigate Charges Against the: Food, Tobacco, Agricultural and Allied Workers of America; International Union of Mine, Mille and Smelter Workers; United Office and Professional Workers of America; United Public Workers of America., Feb 1950 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - CIO 11th Convention, Cleveland (Nov. 1949)Contents: typescripts of DB articles, and clippings, covering the lead-up to the convention, the convention and its aftermath., 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - CIO Left-Wing Labor Leaders Meeting, Sep 1949-Oct 1949 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Clippings on Communism and Labor, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The End of the (Party) LineDescription: typescript (6 p.) of article, including a useful table, on the decline/demise of Communist-led unions, Jan 30, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Interviews with James Carey, Henry Fleischer, and Clint GoldenContents: covers Phil Murray, Lee Pressman, Len De Caux, and Communist influence in the CIO, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Mitchell, H.L (National Agricultural Workers Union): Letter (3 p.) re Don West, Claude Williams, Owen H. Whitfield (leading Southern Communists and/or fellow travelers), Jan 16, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Jack Stachel and John Steuben: Correspondence and Notes re Organizing Steelworkers in Youngstown, Ohio, Aug 31, 1936-Nov 1936 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - National Labor Relations Board, Communist Influence in.Contents: Includes DB notes on interview with David Saposs, correspondence with Jack Barbash and Morris Weisz (NATO Labor Division)., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Pacific Northwest: News cables to Time (not from DB) re Government Hearings on Individual Communists Contents: principally re Barbara Hartle, Organizational Secretary of the CPUSA's 12th District, convicted Smith Act defendant, then cooperative witness., 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - WFTU/CIO/International Labor Cooperation: Clippings, 1945-1958 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Subseries I:D: Government and Industry's anti Communist campaign
    General aspects of the anticommunist campaign are treated in this section. Articles and reports concerning government actions against union officials associated with the CPUSA and business reports illustrating private harassment of communists and "left wingers" in the labor movement are included here.
    - Bell, Daniel, et al. Press telegrams re anti-communist activity of government and industry., undated, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Clippings and Printed Ephemera re anti-communist activity of government and industry., undated, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Photographs: Herbert Brownell, Apr 1954 (Box A006, Folder 1)
- Series II: The Communist Party U.S.A. and the American Labor Movement: Individual Labor Unions
  The CPUSA has always emphasized the importance of working within the labor movement. Many Party members have been actively involved in CP caucuses within individual unions and, on occasion, Party sympathizers have achieved positions of prominence. This section of the collection is devoted to unions in which there has been active or influential communist participation. It is arranged by union and includes information on Distributive, Processing, and Office Workers of America; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Workers Union; Amalgamated Food Workers Union; United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America; United Rubber, Cork, Linoleum, and Plastic Workers of America; International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the U. S. and Canada; United Public Workers of America; Transport Workers Unions; International Longshoremen and Warehousemen's Union; Packinghouse Workers Union; United Gas, Coke, and Chemical Workers of America; National Maritime Union; Upholsterers International Union; Cloth, Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers International Union; Cutters Local 10; International Ladies' Garment Workers Union; Joint Board of Cloak, Skirt, Dress, and Reefer Makers Unions of New York.
  There are many sources of information about communist activity in the labor movement. Articles, notes, and news clippings reveal some aspects of the CP 's relations with organized labor and make up part of the files of all the unions listed above. For a few unions, these are supplemented by more extensive descriptions; there are a short history of the Packinghouse Workers Union, detailed notes on the Amalgamated Food Workers Union, and a substantial history in manuscript of the United Electrical Workers by William Goldsmith.
  Both public and private efforts to expose communist "subversion" of the labor movement are useful, though not always reliable sources. Reports of congressional hearings concerning the Distributing, Processing, and Office Workers of America; the Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers Union; and the United Electrical Workers; and N. L. R. B. reports regarding the filing of false noncommunist affidavits on the part of the International Fur and Leather Workers Union and the Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers Union, are included in the files of the respective unions. Anticommunist propaganda put out by Oppenheim Collins against Local 1250 of the D. P. O. W. A. is the only example of the private "expose."
  Finally, there is a variety of primary materials. The internal struggles occasioned by CP activities in unions are reflected in leaflets and statements of the Communist and anticommunist factions within the Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union; the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union; and the International Fur and Leather Workers Union and in the report of the trial and expulsion of the United Public Workers of America from the CIO The files of the United Electrical Radio and Machine Workers Union include a class book of the District Fraction Training School for 1937-1938. The material on the needle trades unions is most helpful for an understanding of CP policies and daily activities in the labor movement: the correspondence of Herman Zukowsky with accompanying union material for the period 1926-1937; Trade Union Educational League and Trade Union Unity League material concerning the Cloth, Hat, Cap, and Millinery Workers Union; and reports and statements of the State Board of the Cloak, Skirt, Dress, and Reefer Makers Unions of New York.
  - Subseries II:A: Distributive, Processing and Office Workers of America; Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union
    - Burke, Robert (Alias William Burke) Vice-President DPOWA, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Communism vs Democracy: a Short History of DPOWA & District 65, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Department Store Communists: Clippings, Notes, and ReportsContents: Include several summaries of 1948 interviews by "Levering" with anti-communist union officials (Samuel Wolchok, Jack Altman, et al.), 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - DPOW Clippings, undated, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - DPOW District 65 Clippings, 1952, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Livingston, David - President, District 65, DPOWA, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Osman, Arthur - President, DPOWA, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Paley, Jack - Secretary-Treasurer, District 65, DPOWA, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - RWDSU Committee for a Decent Democratic Trade Union (vs Wolchok)Contents: a thick file containing leaflets, statements, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Subseries II:B: International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers.
    - International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter WorkersIncludes: statements by James Carey., 1936, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Metal Workers HistoryIncludes: affidavit by Sidney Mason re Communist Party work, James Matles; National Radio and Allied Trades internal documents, ca.1930s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II:C: United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (U.E.)
    - Carey, James B., Documents and Publications Relating to., 1940-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - CPUSA District Fraction Training School (UERMWA), Dec 1937-Feb 1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Daily Worker, Excerpts From, 1933, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Emspak, Julius - Biographical File, 1944, 1951, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fitzgerald, Albert - Biographical File, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Goldsmith, William: Untitled Typescript (History of UE), Incomplete? 49 pp., undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Hathaway, Clarence - Biographical File, undated, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Paul M. Herzog, et al v. UERMWA, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Matles, James - Biographical File, undated, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Overgaard, Andrew - Biographical File, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Rivers, Charles - Biographical File, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Sentner, William - Biographical File, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Young, Ruth - Biographical File, undated, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II:D: Cloth, Hat, Cap and Millinery Workers International Union
    - Correspondence of Isidore Feingold and Herman Zukowsky, 1923, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence of Isidore Feingold and Herman Zukowsky, Jan 1928-Jul 1928 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence of Isidore Feingold and Herman Zukowsky, Jul 1928-Oct 1928 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence of Isidore Feingold and Herman Zukowsky, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Internal Documents, Clippings, 1921-1940 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Hand-Written materials (Herman Zukowsky and Isidore Feingold), undated (Box 7, Folder 2)